A Guide to the Frank Repass Brown Papers, 2004.3
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
- Series X. Scrapbooks, Local History 1896, 1913, 1943, undated. (Box 6, 7)
  - Scrapbooks, Local History 1. 1896, 1913, undated., 7 folders. (Box 6)
    - Folder 2. Scrapbooks, Local History 1 - Loose Clippings - Freemasons. Undated.
      This folder contains three original loose newspaper clippings about Masonic Lodges in Alexandria, Virginia and Bristol, Tennessee. Original clippings are housed in an acid-free envelope; photocopies of these clippings on acid-free paper are also in this folder.
    - Folder 3. Scrapbooks, Local History 1 - Loose Clippings - History. Undated.
      This folder contains eleven loose newspapers clippings about Elliot Roosevelt in Abingdon, Virginia, Hedgefield (Mathews) house, Elizabeth Henry Campbell Russell (Madam Russell), Rev. Robert Sheffey, Revolutionary War leader Abram Penn, buffalo herd in Smyth County, capture of James Moore by Indians, Dunmore's Expedition, and Revolutionary War. Original clippings are housed in an acid-free envelope; photocopies of these clippings on acid-free paper are also in this folder.
    - Folder 4. Scrapbooks, Local History 1 - Loose Clippings - Miscellaneous. Undated.
      This folder contains thirteen loose newspaper clippings about Jacksons Ferry bridge, White Top Music Festival, Wythe County World War II draftee list, Shannon & Spangler Hardware Store and Tin Shop, hike by Southwest Virginia Trail Club, V.P.I. alumni in World War II, Wythe County schools, Southwest Virginia Enterprise editor James A. Williams, graduating class of Wytheville Training School, and auction of Laurel Glen Farm. Original clippings are housed in an acid-free envelope; photocopies of these clippings on acid-free paper are also in this folder.
    - Folder 5. Scrapbooks, Local History 1 - Loose Clippings - Obituaries. Undated.
      This folder contains five loose newspaper clippings about C. Bascom Slemp, Ella Repass Umberger, Bessie Noell Williams, and William N. Doak. Original clippings are housed in an acid-free envelope; photocopies of these clippings on acid-free paper are also in this folder.
    - Folder 6. Scrapbooks, Local 1 - Loose Clippings - "Southwest Corner." Undated.
      This folder contains fifteen loose newspaper clippings from Goodridge Wilson's column, "The Southwest Corner." Topics discussed include early physicians, camp meetings, Crawford family, Robert Williams, C. Bascom Slemp, Callaway family, French and Indian War, Sheffey family, James Patton, Corinne Roosevelt Robinson, and politics. Original clippings are housed in an acid-free envelope; photocopies of these clippings on acid-free paper are also in this folder.
    - Folder 7. Scrapbooks, Local History 1 - Loose Booklets & Ephemera. 1896, 1913, 1943 undated.
      This folder contains seven booklets and ephemera items including notes on William Preston, notes on attendance at Burkes Garden Sunday School class (1913), 1943 bulletin from St. John's Lutheran Church, "A Historical Sketch of St. Paul's Lutheran Congregation," by Frank Repass Brown, program "An Evening of Music," at St. Paul Methodist Church, "Constitution of Rural Retreat Evangelical Lutheran Pastorate," and "Constitution of the Congregations of Mt. Airy Pastorate"(1896).
  - Scrapbooks, Local History 2. Undated., 6 folders. (Box 7)
    Local History Scrapbook 2 consists of pages removed from a leather ring binder; these pages have been re-housed in acid-free folders. Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder. Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on families and local history have been photocopied and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
    - Folder 8. Scrapbooks, Local History 2 - p. 1-20. Undated.
      This folder includes information on log cabins, Wythe Raceway, Jonas Huddle, Black Lick, Sluss family, Umberger family, Bedwell family, Steele family, Peery family, and Brown family.
    - Folder 9. Scrapbook, Local History 2 - p. 21-40. Undated.
      This folder includes information on Dutton family, Cline family, Cregger family, Sluss family, Groseclose family, Brown family, Repass family, Spangler family, and Repass Cave in Bland County.
    - Folder 10. Scrapbook, Local History 2 - p. 41-60b. Undated.
      This folder includes information on magistrates, World War II veterans, Spangler family, Freemasons, Battle of Wytheville (1863), New River Valley, Ward family, Price family, and Buchanan family.
    - Folder 11. Scrapbook, Local History 2 - p. 61a-82. Undated.
      This folder includes information on Buchanan family, Patton family, Calhoun family, Evans family, Stalnaker family, Doak family, Hudson family, and Alexander Phillippi, John Greiner, Neff family, Copenhaver family, Kegley family, Leedy family, Capp family, and Cassell family.
    - Folder 12. Scrapbook, Local History 2 - p. 83-106. Undated.
      This folder contains information on Dutton family, Battle of the Cove (1864) and Federal troops' burial site, Mary Draper Ingles, slavery in Wythe County, Laurel Glen farm, and Jacob Repass.
  - Scrapbooks, Local History 3. Undated., 12 folders. (Box 7)
    Local History Scrapbook 3 consists of pages removed from a leather ring binder; these pages have been re-housed in acid-free folders. Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder. Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on families and local history have been photocopied and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
    - Folder 13. Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 1-22. Undated.
      This folder includes typescripts of articles written by F. B. Kegley on Southwest Virginia for Mountain Empire magazine.
    - Folder 14. Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 23-44. Undated.
    - Folder 15. Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 45-64. Undated.
    - Folder 16. Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 65-82. Undated.
      This folder includes an excerpt from German New River Settlement by R. S. A. Heavener.
    - Folder 17. Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 65-102. Undated.
    - Folder 18. Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 103-144. Undated.
      This folder includes information on address by Sherwood Anderson at Ivanhoe High School, Fotheringay, Smithfield, Lead Mines, German settlers in New River Valley, postmasters in Rural Retreat, Michael Cregger, and marriage records from Wythe County.
    - Folder 19. Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 145-166. Undated.
      This folder includes information on Montgomery County marriage records, Wythe County wills, Lantz family, Revolutionary War in Southwest Virginia, Wythe County history, Esther Thompson Crockett, Samuel Crockett, David Doak, James Patton, Dr. Thomas Walker, and Bible records for the Hiral Miller family.
    - Folder 20. Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 167-192. Undated.
      This folder includes information on Hungry Mother State Park, Stalnaker family, Harmon family, log cabins, Rural Retreat, and Johnston Memorial Hospital (Abingdon, Virginia.)
    - Folder 21. Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 193-216. Undated.
      This folder includes information on Johnston Memorial Hospital (Abingdon, Virginia), Greever family, Lancaster County, Pennsylvania, and Molly Tynes.
    - Folder 22. Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 217-236. Undated.
      This folder includes information on Franklin D. Roosevelt's visit to Shenandoah National Park, visit of Eleanor Roosevelt to the White Top Music Festival, Wilderness Road, Appalachian Power Company Claytor Dam project, Henry Grubb family, and early German settlers.
    - Folder 23. Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - unnumbered pages. Undated.
      This folder includes information on James Hays Piper, Shot Tower, Seven Mile Ford, Wythe County formation, and Rural Retreat.
    - Folder 24. Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - loose newspaper clippings. Undated.
      This folder includes both original newspaper clippings and acid-free photocopies. Topics include Wythe Raceway, banks in Rural Retreat, Hungry Mother State Park, cabbage, William Nuckles Doak, Rural Retreat Lake, Rural Retreat post office and postmasters, Bertha Umberger, Marion College, and Confederate monument in East End cemetery.
  - Scrapbooks, Local History 4. Undated., 7 folders. (Box 7)
    Local History Scrapbook 4 consists of pages removed from a leather ring binder; these pages have been re-housed in acid-free folders. Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder. Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on families and local history have been photocopied and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
    - Folder 25. Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - p. 1-38. Undated.
      This folder contains information on the Battle of New Market, Tory Oaks (hanging of Tories in Black Lick during the Revolutionary War), William Gannaway Brownlow, Wythe County postmasters, James McCall home, Wythe Freemasons, Irish immigrants in Wythe, St. John's Lutheran Church, St. Mary's Catholic Church, Presbyterian churches, McCalls (town), and tax records.
    - Folder 26. Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - p. 39-79. Undated.
      This folder contains information on Fleming Church, Molly Tynes, McCalls (town), Mt. Airy, iron industry, slavery in Wythe County, muster roll of Col. Joseph Kent, camp meetings, William Richardson's militia company, Wytheville fire, Robert Sheffey, schools, Esther Thompson Crockett, ministers, mills, R. G. Williams' land grant, and newspapers.
    - Folder 27. Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - p. 80-113. Undated.
      This folder contains information on early settlers, notes from Trans-Allegheny Pioneers by John P. Hale, excerpts from Chalkley's Chronicles of the Scotch-Irish, excerpts from Kegley's Virginia Frontier, and early Wythe County history.
    - Folder 28. Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - p. 114-149. Undated.
      This folder contains information on Revolutionary War militia, Crockett family, roads, churches, and Fort Chiswell.
    - Folder 29. Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - p. 150-179. Undated.
      This folder contains information on Molly Tynes, postmasters, Dr. Thomas Walker, churches, Alexander Smyth, court records, racetrack in Wythe, roads, Newberry Farm, and Lead Mines.
    - Folder 30. Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - p. 180-203. Undated.
      This folder contains information on Austinville, fish hatchery, Francis Mill Creek, Molly Tynes, and Shot Tower.
    - Folder 31. Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - loose newspaper clippings. Undated.
      This folder contains both original newspaper clippings and photocopies on acid-free papers. Topics include Fort Chiswell mansion (McGavock), cattle drive by Robert H. Crockett, E. Lee Trinkle, Sally Haller Wolfenden, Appalachian Power Company, John Neff (WCC faculty), John A. Whitman, Revolutionary War soldiers from Wythe, and Stephen Austin.
  - Scrapbooks, Local History 5. Undated., 7 folders. (Box 7)
    Local History Scrapbook 5 consists of pages removed from a leather ring binder; these pages have been re-housed in acid-free folders. Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder. Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on families and local history have been photocopied and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
    - Folder 32. Scrapbooks, Local History 5 - p. 1-29. Undated.
      This folder contains information on lists of Revolutionary War soldiers from Southwest Virginia and those who swore allegiance to the United States.
    - Folder 33. Scrapbooks, Local History 5 - p. 30-56. Undated.
      This folder contains information on lists of Revolutionary War soldiers and lists of Confederate units and soldiers from Southwest Virginia.
    - Folder 34. Scrapbooks, Local History 5 - p. 57-89. Undated.
      This folder contains information on lists of Confederate veterans, list of servicemen and women in World War II, list of Wythe County militia members, and list of Revolutionary War veterans.
    - Folder 35. Scrapbooks, Local History 5 - p. 90-113. Undated.
      This folder contains information on lists of Confederate solders and list of guards at Charlestown, Virginia in 1859.
    - Folder 36. Scrapbooks, Local History 5 - p. 114-137. Undated.
      This folder contains a newsletter from the Virginia Grand Lodge of Freemasons and lists of Confederate soldiers.
    - Folder 37. Scrapbooks, Local History 5 - p. 138-187. Undated.
      This folder contains lists of Confederate soldiers, history of Smyth County, and history of the Civil War.
    - Folder 38. Scrapbooks, Local History 5 -Christian Herald Articles. Undated.
      This folder contains articles clipped from the Christian Herald on religious history in various states.
  - Scrapbooks, Local History 6 Undated., 2 folders. (Box 7)
    Local History Scrapbook 6 consists of pages removed from a leather ring binder; these pages have been re-housed in acid-free folders. Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder. Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on families and local history have been photocopied and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
    - Folder 39. Scrapbooks, Local History 6 - p. 1-14. Undated.
      This folder contains information on taverns, stage coaches, and early education in Wythe County.
    - Folder 40. Scrapbooks, Local History 6 - p. 15-59. Undated.
      This folder contains a typescript of Louise DuBose's articles on the Allen family and the Hillsville Courthouse shootings.
- Series XI. Memoirs. 1887-1960, undated. (Box 7)
  - Memoirs. Book 1 "Memoirs of Frank R. Brown: Also Facts and Stories About Kin Folks and Friend." 1903-1910, undated. (Box 7)
    Pages are not numbered. Articles listed below are in the order in which Frank Repass Brown placed them. The articles have been removed from the cloth and metal three ring binder and placed in acid-free folders. Photographs have been removed from the memoirs and placed in Series XI; photocopies of these photographs have been placed in this collection. The folder number is indicated below.
    - Folder 1. Memoirs - Book 1 - "Preface, Memoir, Flowers & Garden." Undated.
      Includes: "Preface," "Memoir," and "Flowers and Gardens." Topics (listed in order) found in "Memoir" include young childhood; relationships with sisters and brothers including Matie, Ivan, Daisie, Carrie, Charley, and Gay; relationships with relatives including Aunt Ella Repass, Oden Neff, Aunt Jennie Neff, Frank Harkrader, Tom Dixon, Alice Wetzel, and Maria Woodward; house construction; trips with his father; springs; dogs; church and Sunday school; visits to relatives; memories of church services; Rev. W. R. Brown; Rev. D. S. Fox; Rev. Sieg; Rev. Arndt; Rev. Rhodes, Rev. Griener; Rev. Barringer; Rev. Shumate; Rev. Richard; communion services at church; annual church picnic; and wedding of Mr. and Mrs. T. F. Kidd. "Flowers and Gardens" contains discussion of favorite plants and two photographs (photocopies) of his garden and plants.
    - Folder 2. Memoirs - Book 1 - "My Pet Peeve, Nick Names, Jamestown Exposition, and Miscellaneous Experiences." 1907, undated.
      Topics (listed in order) include music; cemeteries; and dolls. "My Pet Peeve," discusses his dislike of fetching water. Other topics include reading; National Geographic; books and libraries; donation of books to libraries; diaries and scrapbooks; "Nick Names" discusses nicknames given to himself and his brother. Other topics include child labor; jobs; farming; molasses making; chestnut hunting; Wythe County fair. "The Jamestowne Exposition" relates his trip to Jamestown in August 1907. "Miscellaneous Experiences" discusses his grandfather's yard sale and his embarrassment at a church picnic.
    - Memoirs - Book 1 - "My School Days." 1903-1910.
      "My School Days" discusses Huddle School, Rural Retreat High School (RRHS) and teachers Prof. W. R. Bowers, Dorothy Stone, and Cynthia Phillippi. Also included are Annual Announcement of Rural Retreat High School for 1903, 1904, 1907; postcard of RRHS; program for RRHS 1906 artistic exercises; program for RRHS primary and intermediate department artistic exercises for 1906; program for literary societies an class in expression presentation for 1906; program for contests in elocution at RRHS 1906; programs for 1906 and 1910 graduation at RRHS; reports cards for 1904 and 1905; and drawing of RRHS in 1910.
    - Folder 4. Memoirs - Book 1 - "My Trip to Kansas." 1908.
      "My Trip to Kansas" discusses his trip to visit his cousin T. B. Shannon in Iola, Kansas; his case of smallpox; his visit to Iola Carnegie Library; Oklahoma City; and White family. "My Trip" also relates visit with uncle Reuben Repass in Graham, Texas. Included is a smallpox quarantine certificate, five bulletins from First Presbyterian Church in Iola, Kansas; program for Altruistic Club banquet; and two sales slips for R. B. Shannon hardware store.
    - Folder 5. Memoirs - Books 1 - "Rat Decalogue and "Most Unusual Trip." Undated.
      Topics include his experiences at Virginia Polytechnic Institute (V.P.I.); his roommates E. G. Goodwin and Karl Emil Edward Quantz; his work in the agriculture department; and "Rat Decalogue." "A Most Unusual Trip" chronicles his trip on a V.P.I. Agricultural Department train excursion with professors and Virginia Railroad officials. ALso included are six report cards; diploma for two year course in "Practical Agriculture and Farm Mechanics;" blueprint map of the V.P.I. campus, and a letter of recommendation from Prof. N. S. Mayo.
    - Folder 6. Memoirs - Book 1. 1908-1910.
      This folder includes a booklet "Regulations for Virginia Polytechnic Institute 1908," place name card; program for "First Annual Banquet of the Agricultural Students," and graduation programs for 1909 and 1910.
  - Memoirs Book 2., 8 folders. (Box 7)
    Pages are not numbered. Articles listed below are in the order in which Frank Repass Brown placed them. The articles have been removed from the cloth and metal three ring binder and placed in acid-free folders. Photographs have been removed from the memoirs and placed in Series XI; photocopies of these photographs have been placed in this collection. The folder number is indicated below. Photocopies of Memoir Book 2 may be found in the Kegley Library vertical files under "Brown, Frank Repass."
    - Folder 7. Memoirs - Books 2 - "My Life and About My Parents." Undated.
      Topics in "My Life" include the house of his grandfather Brown that was also the first home of his parents. Photocopies of photograph of this farm are included. "My Parents" discusses his father Michael Dallas Brown, and mother Emily Repass Brown and their families. Writings about his father include his character, Civil War service, farming experiences, and his death from peritonitis. He describes his mother's character, family, work, personal habits, cooking ability, and experiences during the Civil War. He also discusses his parents' schooling and love of horses.
    - Folder 8. Memoirs - Book 2 - Grandparents, Michael Cassell, and Michael Brown. Undated.
      This folder includes "My Grandparents and My Great Grandparents" which discusses the Civil War service of grandfather William Henry Brown, uncle Reuben Repass, and grandfather Gordon Repass. He also writes about his grandmother Anna Sharitz Repass, great-grandfather Michael Brown, his great-grandfather Jacob Cassell Sr., and great-great-grandfather John Repass. Articles are titled "Michael Cassell," "Michael Brown's Will," "Notes on the Life of Michael Brown, his Family, and Estate," and "Michael Brown's Grandchildren."
    - Folder 9. Memoirs - Book 2 - "My Kinfolk, Signs and Superstitions, and Sluss Family Massacre." Undated.
      Brown discusses his relatives Newton Umberger, Mike Buchanan, Virginia Umberger Brown (his wife), Anna Marie Brown, Reuben Repass, Rufus Repass, Benjamin Brown, Ephraim Brown, Joseph Rufus Brown, and Sarah Shannon Repass. Also included in this folder is an excerpt from History of Augusta County, Virginia by J. Lewis Peyton. "Signs and Superstitions" examines beliefs of German settlers and "Sluss Family Massacre" discusses attack on Sluss family by native Americans in the 1770s.
    - Folder 10. Memoirs - Book 2 - "Visit to My Grandfather Repass' Last Resting Place, My Personal Expenses, and Pets." 1905-1920.
      In "Visit to My Grandfather Repass' Last Resting Place," Brown discusses visit to Point Lookout, Maryland and Gordon Repass. Other writings include transcripts of Civil War letters written by Brown relatives, walnuts candle stand, his farm pets and disdain of domestic pets, and rocking chairs. Also included is a record of his personal expenses from 1905 to 1920.
    - Folder 11. Memoirs - Book 2 - New House and Moving. 1960
      In "My Visit to the New House," "My Sale, January 21, 1960," "Moving," and "Winter 1960," Brown discusses his experiences in moving into his new house, and snowfall in February and March 1960. Also included is certificate and award from Future Farmers of America.
    - Folder 12. Memoirs - Book 2 - New Year and Animals. Undated.
      Includes articles "New Year Resolutions," "Game and Hunting," "Cranky Idea About Town Children," "The Old Pine Tree," "Pea Fowls," "Watches," and "Christmas.
    - Folder 13. Memoirs - Book 2 - Holidays, Slavery, and Jacob Cassell. Undated.
      Articles include "Thanksgiving," "Cemeteries," "Slavery," "Hidden Treasures or Hidden Gold," and "Jacob Cassell Sr. House." He also discusses name variation, higher education for women, Brown family tradition of equal inheritance for men and women, Marion College and Brown family involvement.
    - Folder 14. Memoirs - Book 2 - Biography and Family. 1915, undated.
      This folder contains photocopies of photographs of Frank Repass Brown as a young child, teenager, college student, and adult. Also included is the booklet, "Life Sketch of Rev. John C. Repass," typescript "The Repass Family by S. S. Cassell, 1915," program "Dramatic Recital of Olive Repass," notes on children of Emily Virginia Repass and Michael Dallas Brown, newspaper obituary of Ivan Josiah Brown, and newspaper clipping regarding election of Frank Repass Brown as honorary Lifetime Director of the Rural Retreat Fair Association.
  - Memoirs - Book 3. 1887, 1960, undated. (Box 7)
    - Folder 15. Memoirs - Book 3. 1887, 1960, undated.
      This folder contains photocopies of photographs of Frank Repass Brown, Virginia Umberger Brown, Michael Dallas Brown, Emily Repass Brown, Josiah Brown, Elizabeth Groseclose Brown, and Anna Sharitz Repass. Other items in this folder include notes on car trip and fuel consumption (November 1960), flyer regarding auction of his farm (1960), baptism card for Virginia Alpha Umberger (1887), and "Southwestern State Hospital," regarding donation of books and magazines.
- Series XII. Photographs. Undated., 8 envelopes. (Box 8)
  - Envelope 1 - Brown Family. Undated., 19 photographs.
    Envelope includes 19 photographs of Emily Repass Brown, Florence E. Repass, Josie Brown Hudson, Carrie Brown, Mattie Brown, Charley Brown, Gay Brown, Elizabeth Groseclose Brown, Josiah Brown, Michael Dallas Brown, Isaac Brown, Hezakiah Brown, William Brown, Daisie Brown, Ivan J. Brown, and Frank Repass Brown.
  - Envelope 2. Frank Repass Brown. Undated., 20 photographs.
    Envelope includes 20 photograph of Frank Repass Brown and wife Virginia Umberger Brown.